The whole purpose of this class is to
teach you how you can design and figure
and install a system on your own. I'm
going to try and roll through this and
just just tell y'all how I configure
fire solar and how you can do it, too.
My main impetus for wanting to teach
this class is I have a moral dilemma
with electricity. I do not think that
humans should buy and sell electricity.
I don't think it's theirs. I think it
was put here on this earth by God for
all of us to use and that people have
been selling it to you. I don't like
that. So, I will give up my time and
energy for free if I can teach you the
only way that I know right now that you
can just snatch it. I want all my big
battery people up here so y'all know who
owns this place and who made this
possible.
>> I'm Dennis Marshall. I started this
company. I came from NASA, lived up in
the mountains of Montana and I said, "I
don't want to pay anyone an electric
bill anymore." And I realized you can
build your own solar system. It's really
not that hard. My goal is just to like
provide people with power to have their
own energy.
>> When else would you get a chance to pick
Parker's brain, my brain, and a NASA
engineer's brain?
>> For free.
>> You [laughter] know, like
It's kind of funny. You retired and
needed solar for your place. I retired
to a van and needed solar for my place
and here we are.
>> With no further ado, I'm going to do my
best to explain solar energy as I
understand it.
>> Just call this simplifying solar cuz the
problem is there's a ton of products and
no information. Who has ever looked up
some type of solar thing on the
interwebs? Did anybody have any relative
success finding clear information? Okay,
well, that changes today. There's a few
things you need to know about solar.
Amps * volts = watts. Ohm's law, Watt's
law, there's a lot of different things
that people call this formula. And next,
you must know the difference between
series and parallel wiring. Yeah,
Parker, series and parallel is a big
thing, isn't it?
>> Mhm.
>> I will say, guys, all of this stuff is
so simple, but because it's so simple,
it's remarkably easy to mess up. And you
wouldn't think it, but you got a 50/50
chance. There's only a positive and a
negative, but you wouldn't believe how
hard it is to get all the way right,
because you have to do very simple
things repetitiously. For energy to
exist, it has to be defined. Energy is
really defined as amps * volts = watts.
And I explain this with a water analogy.
Energy is the river. The watts are how
many total gallons you have. Amps is
current. Let's say how
wide the river is. And we'll say the
volts is how deep the river is. Because
you could have a river that is 30-ft
deep and 40-ft wide, and it could be
1,200 gallons. Or you could have one
that is 60 wide and 20 deep, but still
equal 1,200. But the water in the river
is going to behave massively different.
Because a wide shallow river is going to
move a lot faster, okay? And a deep
narrow river is going to move a lot
slower. They're still going to have the
same amount of gallons in it. You just
got to go and understand what energy is
and how it moves, and then you can learn
to manipulate it. We're going to go to
the next one. Series. If you connect in
series, what does it look like, Parker?
>> Okay, so this is like one thing, and
then you're going to go into the next
thing, and into the next thing.
>> We're going to go plus, minus, plus,
minus. On that solar panel, there are
two leads. One is a positive, and one is
a negative. They only go one way. You
cannot connect the wrong ones together
unless you connect the same ones on a
panel together. Don't do that. But in
series, you literally just take them and
clip them together. And when you do
that, the voltage increases and the
ampacity remains constant. See, we have
volts and amps and watts. Parallel is
the opposite. If you wire in parallel,
you group all your positives together
and all your negatives together, and
then wire them to the terminal blocks
separately. When you do that,
the ampacity increases and the voltage
remains constant. Like I said, 50/50
chance. It's all going to be very
pertinent when we get to that solar
panel. The most importantest thing
is if it clicks, it fits. That is from
my homie Nate Key, who got me started in
solar. That's what we always say, cuz
when you connect something or turn on a
battery or turn on a It will make a
clicky sound of some kind. If it does
not make a clicky sound, you have messed
up. Four things to know: amps times
volts equals watts, series increases
voltage and capacity constant, parallel
and capacity increases voltage is
constant. If it clicks, it fits. We're
going to base everything else off of
those four pieces of information. Who's
intimidated by pages and pages of
electrical documents? It's like reading
a plea bargain. There's a lot of numbers
here, and there's two different
categories, 6.5, 10 kW. You have to
identify the one you're using. Since
they have different powers, they don't
make an entirely different manual, they
just put them both on one. And picking
the correct value is the most important
thing. Everything is just setting up an
equation that balances. And if you know
how to set up an equation, and you set
pick the right values, it will solve
correctly every time. But if one value
is wrong, it will not work. So right
here, I'm going to use the 10 kW model
today. If you look at this, you will see
the MPPT voltage range. Does anybody
know what MPPT stands for?
>> Maximum power point tracking.
>> What does that mean?
>> So there's like a combination of volts
and amps that will come out of your
panel at any given point in time. It's
taking that and converting it into the
ideal combination.
>> Correct.
Correct. But I have to point this out
cuz nobody in here would say MPPT equals
solar. You see MPPT, it means solar.
Write that down. MPPT range, 125 to 450
VDC. What does that mean? VDC strangely
stands for volts of DC, volts of direct
current. And see, once you know that,
even if you don't know what MPPT is, you
know that volts DC, especially that
high, is not coming out of the battery.
That's what you have to have for your
solar. Now there's two values there, 125
and 450. And I say solar's like a
carnival ride. In order to ride this
ride, you must be 125 volts tall, and
you cannot be more than 450 volts tall.
I know a lot about this. I had a lot of
broken hearts at the carnival growing
up. There's also another number. It says
max open circuit voltage. If you look up
here, you see solar inputs, and then all
of these numbers.
Well, I'm starting with the voltage.
We'll do ampacity next because energy
has to have two values to be defined. We
have 550
VDC. I'm going to call that the clip
voltage. It is listed as open circuit
voltage. That's three numbers, 125, 450,
550. We have to have 125 volts to turn
the machine on. If you have 100 volts,
it will not turn on. If you have 460
volts, will it turn on? All right, this
is the confusing part. It will. This is
the the one thing that you're going to
learn is there's always two values on
your solar charts, an operating voltage
and a clip voltage. That means the clip
voltage is 550. You can produce energy
up to 450 volts, but if you exceed 550
volts for any reason, the system will
short. It will turn off. That means you
can float up 450, 460, 470, 480, 490,
510. You're not going to get any more
power out of it. You cannot squeeze the
lemon for any more juice, but the system
will still work. If you exceed 550, it
will clip, and none of your solar panels
would be producing energy at all. The
next is our power input. You see power
input, and there's a key thing I want
you to look for on this. It has the
letter A next to it. What does A stand
for? Stands for amps. Now, you should be
looking for something in there because
you know, this is where you got to
start. You have got to get this equation
every time, or you're not going to be
right. You have to get all three values
from here, and strangely, you only have
to get two values cuz you can find the
third one from two values. So, we know
we have our voltage, but what is our
ampacity? Now, if you look on here,
there's two different numbers, 18A +
18A, 22A + 22A. We're using the 10 kW,
so we're going to look at the 22A cuz
it's under that column. 22 amps is our
our ampacity. We cannot exceed ampacity
ever. What happens if you exceed
ampacity? Breaker trip, wire melt,
something blows up. Ampacity is the the
power behind it. I'm going to tell you
all this and then I'm going to show you
the easy way that you can do it cuz I
put all this in computer coding on a
free program that will do it for you.
But, I will teach you math before I give
you a damn calculator. 125 to 450 volts,
no more than 550, and we cannot exceed
22 amps for any reason. Where are the
electrical specifications on this solar
panel? Now, just so you know, every
electrical device in America has to have
a data plate. It's right here. Tiny tiny
little writing. I have one up here that
you can see, and you're going to see V A
V A W. Amps times volts equal watts.
See, it's medical coding. Once you know
what to look for, W means watts. VDC
means volts DC. VAC means
volts AC. And notice one is smaller and
one is bigger. I'm going to get to that
in a minute. That relates back to have a
smaller VDC and a higher VDC. Does
anybody see how this is lining up? We're
going to go with the open circuit VOC,
50.85
volts. Then I'm going to go ahead and
give you the operating voltage, the
Vmax, 41.96
volts. Then I'm going to give you short
circuit current, the ISC, 11.37
amps, and the max operating current,
10.61 amps. Can anybody tell me how many
watts this panel produces off of the
information on the board? Whenever
you're doing your electrical
calculations for how much energy it's
going to produce, use the smaller
number. Just write that down. Use the
little guy. I like this phrase, the
little guy. There are two bigger numbers
and two smaller numbers. There's two
volts and two amps. Somebody multiply
those two numbers together.
>> 61 not 16. 10.61
* 41.96
>> I bet you if somebody goes and looks,
that says 445 watt panel.
>> Yes, it does.
>> Huh? If our MPPT range is right here,
how many panels can I put on there?
That's the question. Well, let's see.
There was some secondary information
that you needed to remember. Because
what do we want to do? Well, let's say
if they're operating at I'm going to
round up for the sake of math, 42.
And this is about standard. Most panels
that you're going to see, the bigger
panels, I don't really mess with the
smaller panels a whole lot. I figure if
you're going to set a panel, set the
biggest one you can. But they usually
are operating between the 35 and 50
range. Now, if I have one operating at
42 volts, 10.61 amps, what happens if I
hook two of them together in series?
Series, if you connect in series, I take
two of them panels, put negative to
positive, and test it with a meter, what
will it read? 84 volts. Are we tall
enough to ride this ride?
>> Yeah.
>> I'm old. I'm old.
>> Nope. Who [clears throat] has ever
hooked up a solar system and had voltage
going in but nothing's charging? This
was your problem. I learned because I
had uh one panel on a 48 volt system
which requires 60, and I was cussing for
2 days to figure out WHY IT WOULDN'T
CHARGE. THERE'S VOLTAGE GOING I didn't
read the specs.
>> So, you would need three.
>> At least. So, three of them. Do we want
to minimize or maximize the input?
>> We maximize.
>> Okay. I'm going to show you one other
thing that I I left off. This has a
wattage rating as well. It says
5,500 watts plus 5,500 watts. That's
kind of confusing. There's two values
that are exactly the same but they're
separated. Same thing with the ampacity,
22 amp and 22 amp. Why? That tells you
that there are two separate solar inputs
on this. Each one will take 22 amps and
55 watts. If you do the math there and
divide 5500 by 22,
tell me what you get. That's somewhere
around, you know, 450. We want to get as
close as we can to 450 without exceeding
550. But in order to do that, we have to
figure our higher voltage. You see, our
open circuit. Just so you know, open
circuit means the time when the sun is a
certain direction and intensity, the
panel will float from its operating
voltage of around 42 all the way up to
50. But you're not going to get any more
power out of it. See, that's the
difference. The voltage will increase,
but you get no more energy. Why do you
have to know that? Why is that
pertinent? Our clip voltage. You didn't
know about the clip voltage, you'd say,
"41.96 450 volts? Should I put 10 in
there? 420 volts?" If we did 41.96
* 10 in series, that would be
419.6
volts. Check mark, correct? Ah, but you
didn't think about your open circuit.
Let's do 10 * 50.85.
Wait a minute, we're still good. I
almost could get 11. Now, so here's what
you want to do to maximize your solar.
You want to get as close as you can to
that clip voltage without exceeding.
That inverter right there will take
11,000 watts of solar an hour. To put
this in perspective, according to the
DOE, the standard of average American
home takes 30 kWh a day. That inverter
under ideal conditions will make it less
than 3 hours.
>> [laughter]
>> Technology's come a long way. We could
get 10 panels on here. It checks out. If
you did 11, you would walk in there one
day about high noon and your solar
system would be blank. And you go,
"What? The sun's out." So, those are
your two voltages. The other thing I did
not mention was ampacity. Our operating
ampacity is 10.61 amps. What is our clip
ampacity? 22. Are we good? Yeah. 11.37,
it'll float up that way under 22. Now,
this is where you learn how to optimize
a system. We can go up to 22 amps, but
we're only going to 10.61. So, what I
would do is find another panel for this
system because I can't wire this in
parallel. Now, what would happen if we
took the same string that's operating at
10.
61 amps, 419 volts. What will happen if
we make an identical string? We clip 10
more together, positive, negative,
positive, negative, and then we take our
main positive and negative from each one
and wire them together. What will
happen? Ampacity increases, voltage
constant. That means this would then go
to 21.22.
Wait a minute. I was wrong. This is
perfect. I thought Oh, the ampacity goes
up to 11.3.
Meaning, this would float up to
somewhere around 22.74,
which will clip your ampacity because of
the open circuit. This one is so close,
but it is .74
over. And if you did not know that, your
system will be cutting in and out
intermittently at random times and you
would have no idea why. I've seen this a
bunch cuz it's so close. If this was 11,
it'd be perfect, but it's a little bit
high.
So, what you want to do is find a panel
that approaches the ampacity and the
voltage as close as you can, and there's
every shape and size of panel in
existence out there. They're different
dimensions, different voltages. If it
says 450 volts, there's no guarantee
that it operates at this voltage.
Why? Well, it could have a higher
ampacity and a lower voltage to get it
450 watts. You have to read the
electrical specs on every single thing.
And it doesn't take long once you know
it, but you want to maximize the system.
Does anybody have any questions here?
Good explanation? How am I doing?
>> Pretty damn good.
>> All right.
Okay, now I'm going to show you the easy
way. So,
this is on my website. You can do this
for free. The only thing on this is you
have to make a free login with your
email address and your email only, and
that is pertinent uh because you can
email yourself a professional wiring
diagram showing you how to install your
system. This is Fells Calc. I put it on
there.
Um and this will tell you if your system
is electrically compatible, if you have
all the values. Ideally, what I want you
to be able to do is print off your
wiring diagram and your material and
order your materials right there.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Um you know, and and I tried to make it
pretty easy. There's a lot of other
parts to this. Obviously, like I could
stay here all day and teach you the
whole thing, but I'm going to try and
teach you the pertinent enough to make
you dangerous.
>> Yeah.
>> Right.
>> [laughter]
>> And I'm going to tell you with solar, it
takes three. You install one with me
today,
you'll get it.
Then you'll go do one yourself and have
one of the worst times of your life
cuz I'm not here.
We have sent the Holy Spirit of Parker
to help you.
>> [laughter]
>> But
but you'll you'll kind of struggle
through it, and after you figure out all
your little mistakes, you'll get that
system going, and then you'll install
another one, and you'll have it down
pat. And after that, you can go teach
somebody else. That's really what I want
is more people knowing how to do this.
Now, I'm not trying to sell you
anything. I'm trying to give you free
information.